Hello everyone. Today we're
kicking off a series of
lectures on respiratory
physiology and our first
lecture will be on airways
and pulmonary blood flow.
I'm Dr. Jörg Lehest. I'm a
professor of neuroscience.
I'm also the chair
of the Department of
Biomedical Sciences,
the founding director of
our Center for Health
Policy Research and also
the director of our BMS
Master's Bridge program.
Welcome.
These are the learning
objectives that go with
this lecture. So we
will be covering what's
covered by learning
objectives. No more, no less.
Most of these learning
objectives focus on
structural function
relationships. So it's really
important to me that
you learn concepts
and not rogue knowledge.
And that's why we're
exploring the why's more
often than the what.
it's also important to me
that you start understanding
how socioeconomics play
into health and I'm
going to give you an
example later in the lecture
when talking about respiration
we're actually talking
about two different things
we're talking about either
external respiration which
is marked by the gas exchange
that happens in the alveoli
in the lungs so this
is air in here and this is
the bloodstream and in the
alveoli of the lungs, carbon
dioxide is released as waste
and oxygen is being taken
up into the bloodstream.
Then the other part of
the respiratory system is
internal respiration and
there the opposite happens. So
the oxygen that was just
absorbed into the bloodstream
is being handed off to
the target tissues, a
muscle for instance, and
the carbon dioxide that
results from work of
this tissue is being
released into the bloodstream
for waste disposal.
Oftentimes, when talking
about respiration and gas
exchange, there's a focus
on oxygen only, but it's
equally important to talk
about carbon dioxide.
So here in this image,
you can see an example of
how target tissues muscle
for instance that's the
opaque releases carbon dioxide
through the interstitial
fluid into the capillary
that picks it up and
then there are three things
that can happen to the
carbon dioxide so either
it can bind to red blood
cells directly and be carried
to the lungs that way,
it can dissolve in
the bloodstream and be
carried that way, or,
and that's the majority,
it can become part of the
bicarbonate buffer system.
So that is the system
that buffers our blood.
And so here, as part of the
bicarbonate buffer system,
carbon dioxide enters
the red blood cell,
it gets combined with
water into carbonic
acid, and then when an
oxygen is split off,
that leaves us with
bicarbonate itself.
This is tied and pictured
here on the red blood cell
because the enzyme that
accomplishes those two
reactions, the carbonic
anhydrase, you can actually
do do this in both
directions is tied to the red
blood cell now look at the
respiratory anatomy and
particularly the respiratory
tree that is everything
below the nasopharynx which
would be up here begins
with the trachea and ends
with the alveolar sacs
most noteworthy is that
the system is split into
two main components into
a conducting zone and then
respiratory zone as the
name suggests conduction of
air down to level 16 occurs
without participation
in gas exchange and
then gas exchange occurs
below level 16 in all
of those structures
another thing that is
obvious is that there are
these white structures
and rings and patches
associated with the
trachea and the bronchi and
those are cartilage rings
or patches and they're
in place to keep the
large conducting airways
open. We don't have that
as we go further down.
We have smooth muscle
associated almost with the
entire system and all the way
down and into the alveolar
ducts and so that means
that the regulation of
airflow can occur in those
in all of those areas
unfortunately that is
where some individuals have
developed respiratory issues
so people that are suffering
from asthma they have
undue contraction of those
smooth muscles down here
which impedes airflow.
We also have cilia that are
associated with the system
all the way down into the
respiratory bronchioles.
So when pathogens get into
the system or just dust and
other debris that we breathe
in, the cilia ensure that
this gets moved up. It's
called the respiratory
elevator and then we either
swallow it or we spit it out.
here a different view of
the respiratory tree we're
starting with one trachea
which then splits into two
main bronchosis which then
leads us to the smallest
level of the bronchi and
then bronchioles here with
the terminal bronchioles
the smaller bronchi are
the last structures that
have cartilage support and
down to level 16 here at
level 16 we find the terminal
bronchioles so that is
where the conducting system
ends and that's where the
respiratory system where
gas exchange occurs begins
let's now look at the
conducting zone of the
respiratory system the conducting
zone has three major
functions so they are listed
here to humidify the air
that comes in to warm up
the air as it comes in
and most importantly to
filter so and this filtration
happens by debris dust or
pathogens dissolving in
the mucus that is lining
the system and then the
cilia that are in the system,
they beat this mucus
upwards, as you can see here,
all the way down here.
Things go up and then they
can be either swallowed,
they can be released
either via mouth or we are
blowing our noses, and
that way the system stays
clean and pathogen free,
and this is called the
mucociliary elevator that
accomplishes this work.
Fortunately, most of our
breathing works without
much thinking about it,
and that's because it's
largely under autonomic
regulation, and that is
accomplished via the two
main systems that you've
already explored in different
contexts, sympathetic
and parasympathetic
division. The sympathetic
division emerges at
the spinal cord level
T1234, and it works via
beta-adrenergic receptors.
Here are some
substances and chemicals
that we use for
treatments that can
bind and activate
those receptors.
Amongst those are
epinephrine, of
course, isoproteranol,
and albuterol.
This is familiar to people
that are familiar with
asthma, for instance. So
that's when we use this
chemical to widen airway
diameter. Makes a lot of
sense that the sympathetic
division takes care of
this because it's a fight
or flight response. And
when we're in that mode,
we need to breathe more.
The parasympathetic
division of this autonomic
process works mainly via the
vagus nerve. that's cranial
nerve 10 and it works
through muscarinic
acetylcholine receptors and
the goal here is to narrow
airways bronchoconstriction
or narrowing of the airways
can range from bothersome
to life-threatening
and can be triggered by any
of those depicted triggers
so allergies in most
cases but also viral
infections so a lot of long
COVID that we see right now
is due to the effect of
the COVID-19 virus during
infection also individuals
that are suffering from
gastro esophageal reflux
disease they produce too
much stomach acid and then
that acid can get into
the respiratory tree
and cause damage
and with that
irritation that this
causes can cause
bronchoconstriction.
I would like to read
the next slide to you.
It's important to
realize how resources
matter in terms of health
and health care and so that's
what we call the social
determinants of health,
sometimes socioeconomic
determinants of health, to make
the point that resources
are at the center of this.
I'm also mentioning this to
you because I'm the director
of the NYTCOM Center of
Health Policy, and we look
into those issues, we do
research, I do research with
my students on those issues,
and if you're interested,
then I would encourage you
to reach out to me. All
right, so this is the
case of Dylan, who is a
seven-year-old African
-American male presenting to
the emergency department
of a large medical center.
He presents with
shortness of breath,
chest pain, and
a wheezing cough.
Dylan's mother is crying and
afraid that he
could asphyxiate.
The treating physician
manages to calm her down
and notes that Dylan
has been suffering from
similar but less severe
symptoms, including
episodic cough, wheezes,
shortness of breath,
and chest tightness with
itchy red watery eyes
and stuffy runny nose
for more than a year.
When asked about their
living circumstances, Dylan's
mother explains that she,
her son, and one younger
sibling live in a small one
-bedroom apartment in Washington
Heights, Manhattan, New
York, where she sleeps on
the couch. She's working
in a local bakery on the
corner, but recently had to
reduce her hours due to her
issue with child care she
also states that she's behind
with the rent and that her
landlord is ignoring her
plea to fix or replace her
window air conditioning
unit subjecting her and her
children to hot low quality
air during the summer months
which is likely triggering
dylan's asthma attack well
thank you for listening
now briefly back with some
respiratory anatomy you can
see here that as we move
from the conducting zone
into the respiratory zone where
things are getting smaller
and smaller we also see
a tremendous increase in
surface area so if one
unfolded the entire human lung
it would be actually as
big as a tennis court and
that is quite amazing
but it also makes sense
because what the system
is supposed to accomplish
in the respiratory zone
is gas exchange and the
bigger the system, the
easier the gas exchange.
So just to remind you
that the split between
conducting and
respiratory zone happens
about generation 16.
That's right here
at the level of the
terminal bronchioles.
The slide depicts the
end of the respiratory
tree at generation
23. You can see the
alveolus here with its
airspace and white.
That is where gas
exchanges between the
air and the interstitial
fluid. That's the
blue portion. And
then between the
interstitial fluid into
the nearby capillary.
So it's actually quite
amazing that all of these
gases, CO2 and carbon dioxide,
which are physiologically
important to us, that
they have to penetrate two
levels of cells, which are
the pneumocytes and also
capillary endothelial cells,
plus a level of liquid.
But these distances are
very small, and as depicted
in the slide before, the
system is enormously large,
and that's how things get
accomplished efficiently.
It's noteworthy that alveoli
are aligned by two types
of cells. 90% are these type
1 pneumocytes they're just
lining cells they're
metabolically not super active
the ones that are really active
are the type 2 pneumocytes
and they contain lamellar
bodies and through those
lamellar bodies they release
surfactant so surfactant
we'll talk about in the
next few slides what it does
it's like a soapy molecule
um these type new mono
pneumocytes not only release
surfactants they're also the
stem cells of the system
and if anything gets damaged
either type 1 or type 2 then
they're replaced with stem
cell with cells that are
coming from this type 2
pneumocyte stem cell it's
important to realize that our
body works with two separate
circulatory systems the one
is the pulmonary circuit and
the other is the systemic
circuit so the pulmonary
circuit only serves the
lungs, and it's important that
this is a dedicated circuit
because it works with low
blood pressure, so whereas
the systemic circuit works
with high blood pressure.
This is important in terms
of the pulmonary circuit
because the structures, as
you've seen in the previous
slides, that facilitate
gas exchange are very small
and delicate, and if the
system was a high-pressure
system then a that would
not allow enough time for
gas exchange and be it would
also destroy the system
this slide is very helpful
for two reasons a it shows
the intricacy of the
pulmonary circulation so blood
flows in our deoxygenated
blood through the pulmonary
artery and that's the only
artery in our body that
carries blood that's low in
oxygen and all the way down
to the alveoli when gas
exchange occurs and then
rich blood rich in oxygen
then returns to the system
to the heart in this case
through the pulmonary vein.
Another thing that you
can see here is the smooth
muscle fibers that are
wrapped tightly around the
bronchioles and all the
way down to the terminal
bronchioles. And you can imagine
that if you have constriction
here, that that can
cause a huge problem. So
that is the problem that
we looked at with Dylan's
case. So that's exactly
what happens when the system
gets irritated for instance
with allergens then
these smooth muscle fibers
they contract and they close
off those airways causing
issues with respiration
whereas the pulmonary
circulation that we just looked
at is a low pressure system
for the reasons outlined
there's also a high pressure
system that serves the
lung A high-pressure system
is called the bronchial
circulation, and it's part
of the systemic circulation.
And so it's facilitated
by the bronchial arteries
and veins and their arterials
and venules, and their
function is to feed the
tissues the larger portions
of the respiratory tree
that are too large to
help themselves from the
oxygen that they conduct.
This slide here depicts a
good example of a shunt.
So a shunt is a
connection between two
systems that are
otherwise separate.
You've already learned
now why it is important
to keep systemic and pulmonary
circulation separate.
However, there are
some connecting points.
And so in this example
here, we're looking at the
pulmonary artery that brings
deoxygenated blood into
the alveoli, then the gas
exchange occurs and blood
leaves the alveoli oxygenated
and then comes in a vessel
from the bronchial system
and then adds oxygen-poor
blood into the freshly
oxygenated portion of blood.
So here the two systems
combine through what's known
as a bronchopulmonary
anastomosis and about two
-thirds of the bronchial blood
supply that supplies the
bronchial tree drain this way
through bronchopulmonary
anastomosis.
Now you see right away
what the consequence is.
So you can see that the
blood oxygen concentration
here in this portion
before the anastomosis
happens actually higher
than after. So by
adding this bronchial
blood to the pulmonary
circuit, the blood oxygen
content slightly drops.
Water, as you can see,
has a tendency to achieve
its lowest volume, and
that is done via surface
tension. So wherever you
have water molecules, they're
trying to stick to each
other, and that also
happens here inside the
alveolus. So these arrows here
are pointing towards the
forces that exist that
actually want to collapse
the alveolus so that the
water that lines it can
form the smallest volume.
This tendency of alveoli
to collapse because of
the water film that lines
it is described by the
Laplace law, which is the
pressure to collapse P
equaling 2 pi divided by
the radius of this alveolus.
It's important to realize
that this collapsing
pressure is actually
inversely proportional to the
radius of an alveolus. In
other words, the smaller
the alveolus, the closer
the water molecules are to
each other, the higher
the pressure to collapse.
The opposite is true for
a larger alveolus. So
the bigger the alveolus
gets, the farther the water
molecules are from each
other, the less the
pressure to collapse. Now
there's one molecule that
prevents this collapse and
it's called surfactant.
Our body makes it type
2 pneumocytes as we've
already explored and
that increases compliance
of these alveolar spaces
and also over wetting.
This depicts the fate of
one of the water molecules
that are inside and
lining and alveolus so
the ones that are in the
center of the drop they
pull equally on each other
on their surroundings
the ones that are at the
surface area at the boundary
area between air here
white and blue which is
the water film they produce
more bonds towards the
water molecules that are
inside this drop because
they have nothing to bond
here with the air and
that is what produces the
collapsing force and gives
rise to the Laplace law
that we just looked at.
Here comes dipalmitoyl
phosphatidylcholine DPPC to
the rescue so it's also
known as surfactant and the
surfactant molecule is a
phospholipid and it inserts
in between the water
molecules and breaks up the
surface tension in that
sense it actually works very
much like soap and chemically
that's also what it looks
like you have a really good
pulmonary anatomy practice
question for you a team
of biomedical researchers
is investigating lung
physiology using an animal
model they temporarily
occlude the pulmonary artery
supplying the left lung
while leaving the bronchial
arteries intact they observe
that while gas exchange
in the left lung drops to
near zero the structural
tissues of the left conducting
airways remain healthy
and viable which of the
following concepts best
explains why the tissues
of the conducting airways
survived despite the occlusion
of the pulmonary artery
okay so there are several
layers to this um what i
would like you to do in
general is to not only focus on
the right answer choice
but also i would like you
to explore why the distractors
are incorrect um it's
a very important very
important process in learning
and it will help you
to hinge the piece of
information that we're
actually looking for to the
broader context so let's
go through all of the
answer choices one by
one and let's look why
how about a the pulmonary
artery normally supplies
oxygen-rich blood to the
conducting airways but
the bronchial arteries
quickly reversed their flow
to compensate um that flow
reversal never happens
and what kind of blood
is it that the pulmonary
artery supplies so first
of all the pulmonary artery
is part of the pulmonary
circulation that's a
low pressure circulation
slow pressure to not
damage the alveoli that
this is going towards and
it actually is the only
case in the body where an
artery carries oxygen poor
blood so the pulmonary
artery carries oxygen
poor blood into the lungs,
which is meant to re
-oxygenate in the alveoli.
How about C? The
pulmonary circulation is a
high-pressure system meant
for tissue nutrition,
while the bronchial
circulation is
exclusively used for
alveolar gas exchange.
Well, it's actually just
the opposite. So, the
pulmonary circulation is
the low-pressure circulatory
system, and as I said
before, that's to not damage
the very fragile alveoli,
and the bronchial circulation
is actually the system
that is used to oxygenate
the tissues that partake
in the pulmonary system.
Let's go to D. The
alveolar capillary bed
supplied by the
pulmonary artery provides
the primary oxygen
source for the thick
walls of the main and
segmental bronchi.
So if you remember
the anatomy slide,
then you know that
there's a lot of tissue
associated with the
segmental bronchi.
You also know that
diffusion of oxygen is very
much a function of distance.
So in essence, these
tissues that we're
talking about, namely the
segmental bronchi, they're
way too thick to be just
fed by the oxygen that
may diffuse from the
pulmonary circulation. So
that makes D incorrect.
E, both the pulmonary and
bronchial arterial systems
originate directly from
the right ventricle,
allowing total redundant
backup of nutrient delivery.
so which one originates from
the right ventricle remember
standing in front of the
person left is right and
right is left so the pulmonary
artery is actually what
originates from the right
ventricle and where does
the bronchial artery come
from of course the aorta so
that makes e incorrect so
which means one left b is the
correct choice the bronchial
circulation branches from
the systemic arterial tree
to provide oxygen oxygenated
blood directly to the
structural walls of the
conducting airways and um
that's exactly what's going on
why these stay healthy um
yeah so um this question of
course is just an example
and the topic is much broader
but we'll talk more about
it in the events that are
associated with the lecture
all right thank you bye-bye
with this and the other
lectures in this system I
follow very closely to the
book that's Constanzo's.
And so any other resources
that I would like you
to consult and look at
can be found in the class
preparation guide that
goes with this lecture.
Constanzo has a very good
summary portion, so please
have a look at that. There
are also self-quizzing
questions. They're not
medical board style, but they
will allow you to test
yourself on the important
concepts that we covered
today and also going forward
with the other lectures
so thank you very much for
your attention if you would
be so kind give me some
feedback so that works
through the feedback link
right here tell me what went
well what in your opinion
needs work and then we take
it from there Thank you.